Guide to the Vernon L. Smith Papers, 1938-2019 RL.01220
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Vernon L. Smith papers
1938-2019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Smith, Vernon L.
RL.01220
238 Linear Feet 190 record cartons.
3.3 Gigabytes Three sets.
Vernon Smith (born 1927) is a Nobel Prize winner and Professor of Economics and Law at Chapman University. This collection primarily documents his professional life through his correspondence, writings, research, teaching, and professional service. It forms part of the Economists' Papers Archive.
Conditions Governing Access
Access restricted. Some materials in this collection contain potentially sensitive information. Contact Research Services for access.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Some materials are electronic records that require special equipment. Contact Research Services with questions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Vernon L. Smith papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library as gifts from Vernon Smith between 1996-2022.
Arrangement
The Vernon L. Smith papers are arranged into six series: Correspondence, Personal, Print Material, Professional Service, Research and Writings, and Teaching.
Biographical / Historical
Chronology List
1927, Jan. 1 Born in Tucson, AZ
1949 BSEE, California Institute of Technology
1952 MA, University of Kansas
1955 PhD,Harvard University
1951-1952 Instructor of Economics, University of Kansas
1954-1955 Economist, Harvard Economics Research Project
1955-1967 Assistant/Associate/(Full) Professor, Purdue University
1957 "On the Use of Engineering Data and Statistical Techniques in the Analysis of Production and Technological Change: Fuel Requirements in the Trucking Industry", Econometrica
1957-1959 Research Consultant, RAND Corporation
1958 (with K. David and J. Wiley) Economics: An Analytical Approach
1958-1959 Faculty Research Fellow, Ford Foundation
1961 Investment and Production
1962 "An Experimental Study of Market Behavior", Journal of Political Economy
1967-1968 Professor of Economics, Brown University
1968-1975 Professor of Economics, University of Massachusetts
1975-2001 Professor of Economics, University of Arizona
1977 "The Principle of Unanimity and Voluntary Consent in Social Choice," Journal of Political Economy
1979 Research in Experimental Economics, vol. 1 (editor)
1982 Research in Experimental Economics, vol. 2 (editor)
1983 Editorial Board, The Cato Journal
1985 Associate Editor, Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization
1985 Research in Experimental Economics, vol. 3 (editor)
1986-1987 Founding President, Economic Science Association (ESA)
1986-2001 Research Director, Economics Science Laboratory (ESL), University of Arizona
1992 Editorial and Advisory Boards, Economic Theory
1993 Consultant and lecturer, Prospect Electricity, Australia
1994 "Preferences, Property Rights and Anonymity in Bargaining Games," Games and Economic Behavior
2001-2008 Professor of Economics and Law and founding Director of Interdisciplinary Center for Experimental Science (ICES), George Mason Universiy (along with three colleagues from Arizona)
2002 Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Sciences for his work on empirical economic analysis, especially related to alternative market mechanisms
2008-present Professor of Economics and Law, George L. Argyros Endowed Chair in Finance and Economics, and founder of Economic Science Institute (ESI), Chapman University
Related Materials
Alvin Roth papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Raymond C. Battalio and John B. Van Huyck papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of these papers reside in Research and Writings, which contains extensive files of his research notes, reprints, and revisions of working papers by himself and others with annotations. Broadly speaking, these files document important developments in experimental economics and his contributions to this field of study. Primary subjects include the development of a methodology for experimental economics; the implementation of experimental economics into the studies of asset trading, capital investment, game theory, environmental economics, price behavior, strategic decision making, and utilities; and the behavior toward, as well as the psychology behind, economic decisions. Print Materials includes reprints of journal articles by him on similar topics, many of which are also available through the library catalog.
Correspondence contains primarily professional communications concerning comments on his work by other economists, comments on other economists' work (dating from his days editing for several journals), and academic affairs (including recommendations and planning for classes and seminars). The contents of two emails accounts have been transferred and are available, and they contain tens of thousands of messages.
Professional Service and Teaching follow his activities as a faculty member at the universities of Purdue, Brown, Massachusetts, Arizona, George Mason, and Chapman; his roles with organizations such as the National Science Foundation, National Academy of Science, and the Journal of Economic Behavior; and his domestic and international consulting on utility regulation.
Auctions -- Economic aspects; Capital investments; Economics -- Methodology; Economics -- Psychological aspects; Economics -- Simulation methods; Economics -- Study and teaching -- United States; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Experimental economics; Electronic records; Game theory; Markets; Nobel Prize winners; Prices; Production (Economic theory); Public utilities -- Economic aspects; Public utilities -- Prices; Economic Science Association; Economists' Papers Archive; Smith, Vernon L.; University of Arizona. Department of Economics -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1952-2018
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access note. Some materials are electronic records that require special equipment. Contact Research Services with questions.
  Some email files contain social security numbers. Restriction expires in 2077 or upon removal of SSNs.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains mainly professional and academic correspondence, with the bulk from 1971-2007. Includes email from two email accounts--one George Mason and the other America Online (the GMU one also contains an export from Arizona, which is why it dates back to 1993).
  Types of correspondence include: routine academic correspondence, including recommendations for students and faculty, as well as other academic affairs; works of other economists; correspondence concerning Smith's publications; some discussions of economic theory and applications; and professional correspondence, including non-academic recommendations and job offers.
  Majority of the series falls into three main categories: comments on other economists' work, dating to his tenure as editor of several economics journals; comments from colleagues, referees, and other academics on his works; and academic affairs, namely recommendations and routine organizational letters dealing with classes and seminars.
  Notable correspondence includes early exchanges with Paul Samuelson concerning Smith's thesis and graduate level coursework. Also, in one folder of miscellaneous personal correspondence at the end of the series (maybe box 24?), a colleague speaks at length in several letters about the Cuban crisis and civil rights protests.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1952 April-1959 September (Box 1)
  - 1959 September-1963 August (Box 2)
  - 1963 September-1967 August (Box 3)
  - 1967 September-1971 March (Box 4)
  - 1971 February-1974 February (Box 5)
  - 1975 February-1978 January (Box 6)
  - 1978 January-1979 December (Box 7)
  - 1980 January-1982 March (Box 8)
  - 1982 July-1983 November (Box 9)
  - 1983 November-1984 December (Box 10)
  - 1985 January-1986 July (Box 11)
  - 1986 August-1987 November (Box 12)
  - 1987 November-1988 December (Box 13)
  - 1989 January-1990 June (Box 14)
  - 1990 June-1991 September (Box 15)
  - 1991 October-1992 August (Box 16)
  - 1992 September-1993 August (Box 17)
  - 1993 May-1994 September (Box 18)
  - 1994 July-1995 September (Box 19)
  - 1995 October-1997 June (Box 20)
  - 1997 July-1999 June (Box 21)
  - 1999 January-2000 December (Box 22)
  - 2001 January-2003 April (Box 23)
  - 2003 May-2003 December (Box 24)
  - 1981-1988 referee comments (Box 24)
  - 1960-2018 (Box 177)
    Includes folders for Jonathan Hughes, John E. Pfeiffer, Jean-Claude Schoenman, Alan Silberberg, and Henry K. H. Woo, as well as the years 2003-2018.
  - GMU email account, 1993-2007; 50486 email messages; approximately 2.6 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL01220-SET-0002)
    Some files contain social security numbers (indicated in inventory). Restriction expires in 2077 or upon removal of SSNs.
    Contains email messages in MBOX format; includes an export from Arizona with messages that date back to 1993.
  - AOL email account, 2004-2007; 34541 email messages; approximately 385 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01220-SET-0002)
    Contains email messages in MBOX format.
- Personal, 1938-2019
  Contains Smith's academic coursework as a student; clippings; calendars and planners; personal correspondence; and vitae.
  Academic coursework includes course notes, papers, and entrance and final exams from his time as a student at the California Institute of Technology.
  Samuelson material concerns a seminar taught by Samuelson while Smith was pursuing a Ph. D. at Harvard.
  Thesis appendix functions as an explanation of the theories in Smith's main text, utilizing the results of his economic work.
  Clippings deal with the awarding of various professorships to him, and the Arizona Stock Exchange.
  Interview, conducted for the book Economics in Our Times, explores the subject of experimental economics and his role in the study of it.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Academic coursework, 1938-1953 (Box 25)
    - Appendix to thesis, pareto, undated (Box 25)
    - California Institute of Technology, entrance exams, 1938-1946 (Box 25)
    - Cal Tech, exams, 1944-1949 (Box 25)
    - Final Exams, 1947-1948 (Box 25)
    - Economics 611 (Box 25)
    - AM 1b, homework and exams, 1948 (Box 25)
    - Econ 304, development of economic thought to 1870, undated (Box 25)
    - Econ 305, development of economic thought, 1951 (Box 25)
    - Samuelson seminar, 1953 (Box 25)
  - Apex Microtechnology, 1996-1999 (Box 178)
    Includes agendas, minutes, financial records, and other documents from Smith's time on Board of Directors for Apex Microtechnology, a corporation based in Tucson, Arizona that manufacturers precision electrical components.
  - Arlington Economics, 2007-2008 (Box 178)
    Contains operating agreement between Arlington Economics (AE) and founders Thomas Hazlett, David Porter, and Smith. AE is based out of Virginia and consults on experimental economics, telecommunications policy, environmental markets, electricity pricing, and antitrust.
  - Calendars, 1983-1993, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Clippings on Vernon Smith, 1986-1995 (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, family, 1972-1973 and undated (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, personal (Box 25)
  - Economists for Clark (Libertarian Party), 1979-1980 (Box 178)
    Includes few bits of material related to Smith's service as Chair of Economists for Clark. Ed Clark was Libertarian Party's nominee for U. S. President in 1980.
  - Interview with Vernon Smith, undated (Box 25)
  - Memoir, Experimental Economics at Purdue, undated (Box 25)
  - Memorial, Em Weiler (Box 25)
  - Monthly planners, 1980, 1988, 1993-1996 (Box 25)
  - Property and Environmental Research Center; universities, 2010-2019 (Box 178)
    Includes contents of personalized leather folder from Property and Environmental Research Center (PERC) and miscellaneous material from Chapman University (including draft grant agreement with Koch Foundation), University of Alaska Anchorage (including 1 8x10' of him), and University of Arizona.
  - Vitae, 1979, 1988-2001, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Weekly planners, 1997-2001 (Box 26)
  - Weekly planners, 2002-2019 (Box 178)
    Includes flags, notes, and inserts (loose and stapled in).
- Printed Material, 1957-1991
  Consists of two groupings: Clippings and Reprints.
  Clippings was assembled by Smith and consists of newspaper and magazine articles on topics such as auctions, energy resources, experimental economics, fixed prices, government regulation, and the stock exchange.
  Reprints consists of articles written by him or for which he was a contributing author.
  Large portion of the reprints are from a series published by the Purdue University School of Industrial Management Institute for Qualitative Research in Economics and Managment, which later became the Purdue University Herman C. Krannert Graduate School of Industrial Administration, Institute for Research in the Behavior, Economic, and Management Sciences.
  - Clippings, 1975-1987 (Box 27)
  - Purdue reprints, 1957-1977 (Box 178)
    Includes reprints from Purdue University, as well as other academic journals.
  - Reprints, 1957-1967 (Box 28)
  - Reprints, 1968-1979 (Box 29)
  - Reprints, 1980-1985 (Box 30)
  - Reprints, 1985-1991 (Box 31)
  - Reprints, 1992-2006 and undated (Box 173)
- Professional Service, 1968-2019
  Arranged by subject: Games and Economic Behavior, Guest Lectures, Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization, National Academy of Sciences, National Science Foundation, and Presentations and Seminars. These are followed by single folders in original order.
  Contains files on contributions Smith made to professional associations such as the National Science Foundation, the Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization, and the National Academy of Sciences, as well as to the teaching profession and other associations. Contents are varied and include information on guest lectures, seminars, and workshops given by him at both the high school and faculty level, conferences he organized, consultancy positions he held, and professional association committee work he undertook.
  Other material on conferences that he attended can be found in the Research and Writings Series. Many folders deriving from his undergraduate and graduate teaching can be found in the Teaching Series. Because of the nature of his contributions to economics research, much of his work for or with government or non-profit organizations, such as his economic analysis of pollution and recycling for federal government agencies, is found in the Research and Writings Series.
  - Games and economic behavior (Box 32)
  - Guest lectures, 1982-2019 (Box 178, Box 179, Box 180, Box 181, Box 182, Box 183, Box 184)
    Includes itineraries, expense forms, papers, transparencies, and correspondence related to guest lectures/workshops/seminars given by Smith. Some folders clearly indicate that he traveled with his wife Candace, and there are locations across the U. S. and around the world (primarily Europe and Asia). Presentations and seminars in boxes 35-36 probably have material of a similiar nature but from prior to the 1980s.
  - Nihon University Trip, 2005; 122 files; approximately 315 megabytes (Digital-materials RL01220-SET-0003, Folder 1, Optical-disc RL01220-OP-0002)
    Image files.
  - J ournal of Economic Behavior and Organization (Box 33, Box 34)
  - Midwest Economics Association; Mont Pelerin Society; Western Economics Association, 1958-2011 (Box 178)
    Includes speeches delivered at 1958 Midwest Economics Association Meeting; 3 Mont Pelerin Society newsletters (November 1986, February 1988, and Winter 2011); and Westwinds (Western Economics Assocation newsletter), volume 6, number 3.
  - National Academy of Sciences; National Science Foundation (Box 34, Box 35)
  - Presentations and seminars (Box 35, Box 36)
  - Other files (Box 36, Box 37, Box 38A, Box 38B)
  - Other files (Box 176)
- Research and Writings, 1950-2009
  Arranged alphabetically by subseries: Asset Trading, Experimental Economics, Game Theory and Strategic Interactions, Natural Resources and Utilities, Price Behavior, Other Writings, and Writings by Others.
  - Asset Trading, 1971-1998; 16 boxes
    - Asset trading data (Box 49-54)
      Major folder groupings include: mug, 1992; az, 1987-1988; po, posted offer, 1979-1982; and treasury bills.
    - Corporate finance, equilibrium, futures markets, credit rationing, allocation of risk (Box 39-40)
    - Markets (Box 40-47)
      Includes material on market bubbles and crashes, endowments and Coase theorem, preference reversals, rational expectations, and market contestability.
    - Monopolies (Box 47-48)
      Includes Natural Monopoly and Contestable Markets Hypothesis, 1981-1983 and Empirical Study of Decentralized Insitutions of Monopoly Restraint, 1978.
    - Off-floor trading, 1987-1991 (Box 48-49)
  - Experimental Economics, 1974-2004; 27 boxes
    Includes files on the Economics Science Lab at the University of Arizona (including a 2004 legal settlement between Arizona and Smith and three of his colleagues) and National Science Foundation grant proposals.
    Three boxes of writings by other economists and academics in related fields are present; these are arranged alphabetically by author's last name and overlap with the Game Theory and Strategic Interactions subseries.
    The remainder of the folders are arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Alphabetical files, Experimental Economics and Game Theory, A-E (Box 60)
    - Alphabetical files, Experimental Economics and Game Theory, E-M (Box 61)
    - Alphabetical files, Experimental Economics and Game Theory, M-Z (Box 62)
    - Data, 1978-1983 and undated (Box 76)
      Includes charts of weekly experiments.
    - Economics Science Lab, 1983-2000 (Box 55-56)
      Includes budgets, executive committee minutes, lab development and management, and research proposals.
      Additional material may be found interspersed throughout the Natural Resources and Utilities subseries.
    - Economics Science Lab materials (Box 174)
    - Economics Science Lab; International Foundation for Research in Experimental Economics; Cybernomics, 1995-2004 (Box 184, Box 185)
      Includes material related to a 2004 settlement between the University of Arizona (UA) and 4 former UA employees: Smith, Stephen Rassenti, David Porter and Mark Olson. In 1999, a whistleblower complaint alleged irregularities in the affairs of the Economics Science Lab (ESL), International Foundation for Research in Experimental Economics (IFREE), and Cybernomics, Inc (an indepedent consulting firm that developed computer software for economic and market analysis). This led to a university investigation and audit that found that the 4 researchers may have personally benefited from use of UA facilities and other resources on behalf of Cybernomics, in violation of university and regent policies. Cybernomics dissolved in 2003 and the researchers agreed to pay back a portion of their salary, but admitted no wrongdoing. All 4 ended up at George Mason University (GMU), where they founded a reorganized ESL--the Interdisciplinary Center for Economic Science (ICES).
    - Experimental economics and auditing, 1987-1988, 3 folders (Box 63)
    - Experimental economics dictionary entry, 2 folders (Box 63)
    - Economics in the Lab, 1994, 3 folders (Box 63)
    - Energy Department seminars, 1984 and 1990, 2 folders (Box 63)
    - Experimental Economics drafts, notes, and research (Box 63-64)
    - Experimental method and theory, 1982-1988 and 2001 (Box 65-66)
    - Free trade, 1991-1992 (Box 64)
    - Foundation grants
      - Earhart Foundation, 1982 (Box 64)
      - Lynde and Harry Bradley Foundation, 1989 (Box 64)
    - Handbook of Experimental Economics contributing articles, publication information, and reviews, 1996, 15 folders (Box 64)
    - History of Experimental Economic Science at the University of Arizona, 2003-2004; 2 files; approximately 2 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01220-SET-0001)
      Text files; goes into great detail about a scandal that Smith found himself at the center of in the late 1990s/early 2000s at Arizona.
    - Lakatos, 1989, 6 folders (Box 64-65)
      Includes information on the individual and articles on his contribution to the field of experimental economics.
    - Law of unintended consequences, 1998 (Box 65)
    - Liberty Fund lecture, Montana, 1972 (Box 65)
    - Markets and Hayek hypothesis, 1982 and 1999-2001, 6 folders (Box 65)
    - Microeconomics, 7 folders (Box 8)
      Includes manuscript drafts, articles, and notes.
    - Monetary rewards, reward saliency and incentive regulation, 1990-1993 (Box 67-68)
    - NSF grant proposals, 1974-1992 (Box 57-59)
    - Other files (Box 174)
    - Papers in Experimental Economics, 1977-1984 (Box 68-69)
      Includes correspondence with publisher, drafts of contributing essays, and notes.
    - Permission to publish, forms (Box 76)
    - Political economy of exchange, 1986, 9 folders (Box 69)
    - Politics and antitrust regulation, 1980, 3 folders (Box 69)
    - Relevance of Lab Experiment to Testing Resource Allocation, Ann Arbor conference manuscript, notes, and referee reports, 1977 (Box 70)
    - Roth conference, 2 folders (Box 70)
    - Research in Experimental Economics, v. 1-4 (Box 71-75)
      Includes correspondence with contributing authors and publisher, contributing essay drafts, and notes by Smith (series editor).
    - Seminars, articles by others and Smith, notes (Box 70-71)
    - Theory, Experiment and Economics, Journal of Economic Perspectives, 1987-1989, 7 folders (Box 75)
    - Wizard who oversimplified paper and rebuttal (Box 76)
  - Game Theory and Strategic Interactions, 1990-2002; 13 boxes
    See also the Economics Science Lab boxes in the Experimental Economics subseries.
    - Bargaining games, 1991-1994 (Box 77-78)
    - Brain functioning and strategic decision making, 1992-1998, 10 folders (Box 78)
      Contains one color 5x7" photograph of Smith.
    - Centipede games, 1990-1994, 2 folders (Box 78)
    - Cooperation, reciprocity, and trust, 1991-2002 (Box 78-81)
    - Cournot games, 1978, 2000, 3 folders (Box 81)
    - Data (Box 85-90)
      Major folder groupings include: ultimatum, 1991; single blind, 1993; fof, friend or foe, 1997; mach, machiavellian, 1998; asur, assurance, 1995; exbarg, 1995-1997; dictator, 1993-1995.
    - Experimental Economics and Evolutionary Psychology: Forward Signalling, Social Distance and Individuals Rights, 1994 (Box 81)
    - Intentionality, Detection and Mind: Why does game form matter?, 1999-2000 (Box 81-82)
    - Toward a history of game theory, 1992 (Box 82)
    - Monetary rewards and incentives, 1993-2000
      - In ultimatum games, 1993-1994 (Box 82)
      - In strategic interactions, 2000 (Box 82)
    - The Paradox of Power, 1996-1998 (Box 82-83)
    - Players, 1998-2000 (Box 83)
    - Sequential Bargaining and Game Theory Experiments, 1989, 2 folders (Box 84)
    - Ultimatum/Dictator games, 1993-2000 (Box 84)
  - Natural Resources and Utilities, 1969-2005 and undated; 24 boxes
    Arranged alphabetically by subject: natural resources; utilities, electric; utilites, smart markets; and utilities, natural gas.
    Material on natural resources includes proposals (mainly National Science Foundation) and research and writings dealing with issues of exhaustible resources (land, oil, and water) and resource preservation (recycling, waste accumulation, and Exxon Valdez accident assesment). Also includes material for Smith's book Economics of Natural and Exhaustible Resources.